This game is entirely controlled by a
machine learning model.
I've let it play the game multiple times
and it ended up learning how to score
points by itself.
We call this approach reinforcement
learning, and
we'll go through all the steps to make
a model that can play this game, or
even other games.
I'll first explain the problem that we
will solve.
Reinforcement learning comprises two
main components:
the *environment*, in this case a
2D game,
and the *agent*, here, a spaceship in
that game.
The agent interacts with the environment
by moving around and firing projectiles.
It obtains rewards that indicate how
good its actions are.
If the agent collects a point or hits
an enemy, it obtains a positive reward.
If it gets blasted by an enemy, it
obtains a negative reward.
Our goal is to maximize the rewards to
make the agent
as good at playing as possible.
By the way, you can try that game out
if you want.
Open up the project on Github, clone the
repository on your machine,
install the dependencies, and run
the game.
Let's now have a look a models that
we can use.
A basic model for reinforcement learning
is the Q-table.
"Q" stands for "quality", which is an
estimation of the future rewards that
an agent can obtain for a given state
and action.
A Q-table looks like this. The rows
represent all possible states of
the environment, and the columns
represent the possible actions that
an agent can perform. Each cell contains
a Q-value.
Actions that are more likely to lead to
rewards are given a higher Q-value.
For instance, in this state, moving
towards the collectible is more likely
to result in a future reward than
moving away from it,
so moving in this direction corresponds
to a higher Q-value.
When playing the game, the agent can
look up the Q-table to
perform the action with the best quality
given some state of the environment.
Q-tables are easy to understand, but
often impractical.
Before using them, they have to be
filled by performing each action
in all possible states of the
environment and determining
the corresponding Q-values.
That works for simple environments, but
for more complex problems,
we may have to try millions of states
and actions to fill a Q-table.
This approach would not work well in
these cases,
but we can improve it. Instead of using
a large table,
we can approximate it with a machine
learning model.
This is called Deep Q-learning.
The model will not memorize all possible
states and actions like a Q-table,
but will rather learn patterns from
interactions with the game to estimate
which actions are more likely to result
in rewards.
This is more scalable than a Q-Table
because it can
generalize to unseen states, making it
more suitable for complex environments.
We will use an artificial neural
network for this approximation model.
As the name tells, neural networks are
made individual neurons, like this one.
It's a mathematical model that takes
one or multiple values as inputs,
multiplies each input by a weight,
sums the weighted inputs along with a
bias term,
and applies a mathematical operation to
the result.
This operation is called the activation
function, and it's used
to make the neuron model more complex
patterns.
An example of a simple but widely used
activation function is
the rectified linear unit, which cancels
negative values.
The training process modifies the
parameters of the neuron -
that is, its weights and bias, to make
it learn how to play the game.
A single neuron is pretty limited, but
we can create more complex models by
connecting neurons into a neural
network.
These networks are often organized into
layers of neurons that
take the information from the previous
layer and transmit it to the next layer.
In our case, the first layer of the
network, the input layer, receives
footage of the game. The final layer,
the output layer, decides
which button to push. This is used to
control the agent on the screen.
Between these, we can add hidden layers,
which help the network
learn complex patterns from the input.
We can change the number of hidden
layers,
the number of neurons in each layer,
and the way that neurons are connected.
All of these changes are examples of
hyperparameters,
which are settings that define the
architecture of the model.
In theory, we could simply flatten the
input image into a 1D vector
and feed it to a layer of neurons.
This model is called a multilayer
perceptron.
It's a good approach for many problems,
but multilayer perceptrons often
struggle with images because they lack
spatial awareness.
They treat the pixels of the image as
unrelated, separate entities,
which is not effective. In practice,
if you want to understand an image,
you have to look at collections of
pixels to
recognize particular features, like
shapes or edges.
We can do that with convolution, a
mathematical operation where
a small grid - the kernel - slides
across the image to detect features.
For instance, a Sobel operator is
a type of convolution that
highlights edges.
In our model, the convolutional layer
will extract relevant features to
recognize collectibles and enemies from
the input.
The next stage is a fully connected
layer.
The features extracted by the
convolutional layer are flattened
into a one-dimensional vector and fed
to all neurons of that layer.
During training, the parameters of the
neurons will be adjusted to decide
which actions must be performed
depending on the detected features.
Finally, we can plug the fully
connected layer to the output.
This neural network can be written with
the following PyTorch code.
The network will probably not be good
at playing because
it is pretty shallow - meaning that it
doesn't have many layers.
Research has shown that increasing the
depth of a neural network, that is,
increasing its number of layers, can
improve its performances.
But we have to be careful not to add
too many layers because
we then run the risk of overfitting the
model, which means that it will
memorize specific examples seen during
training instead of developing
a general understanding of the game.
Let's summarize: we want to train a
reinforcement learning agent
that will learn to play the game.
We can do that by filling a Q-table and
letting the agent look up
the best action to take for any state.
That table would be large and
impractical, so we instead
approximate it. This approach is known
as Deep Q-learning,
and the neural network that is used is
called a Deep Q-Network.
The next step is to train this network.
For now, its parameters are left at
their default values.
Here's what happens when we let the
untrained model play.
As expected, it performs poorly because
it still hasn't learned
the rules of the game. Here's how
we'll train it:
We create an environment and make the
agent play. This is called an episode.
Episodes are split in discrete steps,
which are game frames.
On each step, the model observes a 2D
image from the game and
predicts a Q-value for all actions.
In other words, it tries to guess the
propensity of each action
to lead to rewards. The agent then
performs the action with the best
Q-value, which
modifies the environment and may result
in a reward, positive or negative.
The agent collects the reward
and observes the new state of the
environment.
The model then predicts the Q-values
for this new state and
selects the highest Q-value. This
represents the future reward that the
agent expects to obtain by performing
this action in a subsequent step.
We now add up the reward that the agent
just collected with the future reward
that it expects to obtain. This is
called the Bellman equation.
It estimates the quality of an action
not just from the immediate reward,
but also from the future rewards that
it expects to get.
Our goal is to make the model estimate
the Bellman equation
as well as possible to identify the
actions that lead to
the highest rewards.
To do that, we want to minimize the
difference between
the Q-value predicted before the action,
and the Q-value calculated
after performing the action and taking
the reward into account.
We call this difference the loss.
The loss is propagated in the network
in the inverse direction
to compute gradients, which are,
roughly speaking,
values that indicate how the parameters
need to be adjusted to minimize
the loss. The process that computes
gradients is called backpropagation.
We then use the gradients retrieved
during backpropagation
to adjust the parameters of the network
with a process called gradient descent.
This makes the model slightly better at
approximating the Bellman equation.
Steps are repeated until the episode
ends, either by losing or reaching
the maximum number of steps. Once the
episode ends, a new one begins,
and the process continues until the
model approximates
the Bellman equation to our
satisfaction.
This graph shows the performances of
the model over its training.
The X-axis shows the number of episodes
and the Y-axis shows the average score
obtained by the agent when we evaluate
it between episodes.
The model gradually improves, but its
performances are very unstable.
We can improve the training process to
stabilize and enhance the performances
of the model. Here are the 5 main
improvements I've added:
First improvement: Add randomness
during training.
This is called exploration - we choose
actions that the neural network
would not have otherwise selected on
its own.
That way, the model experiments a wider
variety of actions and it becomes
better at approximating the Q-table.
Exploration contrasts with exploitation,
which is when we use the action
selected by the network instead of
picking a random one.
We start by relying mostly on
exploration, and as the network becomes
better at selecting the right actions,
we gradually
use more and more exploitation.
Second improvement: Downsize the input.
Raw game footage looks pretty small for
a human, but it still contains
more than 65 thousand pixels for each
frame. The neural network needs
a lot of parameters to process them,
so we can simply downsize the image.
The network now needs fewer parameters
and becomes easier to train.
Third improvement: Combine frames. The
current model looks at a single frame
to decide which action to perform, so
it has a hard time understanding
the motion of objects. We can instead
give it multiple frames.
That way, it will be able to figure out
the direction of projectiles and
collectibles.
Fourth improvement: Increase depth. As
we've seen, adding hidden layers
in the neural network makes it better
at processing data -
provided that you don't add too many.
I've added two convolutional layers -
that will improve performances
without leading to overfitting.
Fifth improvement: Experience replay.
Right now, the model is trained on
consecutive steps,
which are highly correlated. This is
not ideal because
the network might overfit to these
observations.
Instead, we can store the observations
in an experience buffer and
let the model sample random
observations from the buffer
when performing backpropagation and
gradient descent.
That way, it is exposed to a varied set
of experiences,
which improves its ability to
generalize.
Let's recap: we trained a reinforcement
learning model to play a game by itself.
The model is a deep Q network that
predicts which actions are more likely
to result in rewards, and the agent
uses the predictions to score points.
We improved our initial model by using
exploration,
modifying the input data,
increasing depth, and using experience
replay.
These improvements stabilize the
training process and
result in a more efficient model.
The training process is not perfect,
though, and in some cases, the network
does not learn how to play well.
For instance, it may end up learning to
just hide in a corner and spam
the fire button. This is called a local
optimum. It's not the best
strategy overall, but if the network is
not exposed to a varied set of
experiences during its training, it may
learn this strategy at some point and
then stick to it instead of exploring
other potentially better solutions.
To further improve the model and avoid
local optima, we could, for instance:
Use a more advanced model, like a
Dueling Q-Network or
recurrent neural network;
Optimize the rewards obtained by the
agent to prioritize long-term goals and
penalize repetitive actions, or
Adjust the hyperparameters of the model
to improve training.
There's a lot more to reinforcement
learning than what I've laid out
in this video, so let me know if you'd
like to see more.
Also, I encourage you to read these
papers if you want more information
on reinforcement learning.
"Playing Atari with Deep Reinforcement
Learning" covers the
architecture of deep Q networks and
their training process.
"Deep Learning" goes over the
fundamentals of neural networks,
including backpropagation and gradient
descent.
"ImageNet Classification with Deep
Convolutional Neural Networks" presents
a deep learning model for image
classification and
explains convolutional layers.
Everything required to play the game
and replicate the training is
in my Github repository. Training the
model might take some time,
especially if you don't have a
compatible GPU, but
I've also made a simpler game that
takes much less time to train,
so you can try it even on less powerful
systems.
Don't hesitate to check it out.